<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>paraview on Bikulov&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://bikulov.org/tags/paraview/</link>
    <description>Recent content in paraview on Bikulov&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>ru</language>
    <copyright>Network Notes 2022</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 16:31:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bikulov.org/tags/paraview/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Animations from scientific data using Paraview 4.3 and python</title>
      <link>https://bikulov.org/blog/2015/04/05/animations-from-scientific-data-using-paraview-4.3-and-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 16:31:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bikulov.org/blog/2015/04/05/animations-from-scientific-data-using-paraview-4.3-and-python/</guid>
      <description>#&amp;nbsp;Create frames This note describes usage of Paraview 4.3 (contrary to previous note with Paraview before 4.1). Some changes were made:
 command line arguments were added to make code more reusable it works with Paraview extracted from the archive (4.3.1) white background must be specified manually (SetViewProperties(view, Background = [1, 1, 1]) in the code)  Script is tested under Ubuntu 14.04 with Paraview 4.3.1. Paraview was downloaded from official site and extracted to /home/bikulov/bin/ParaView-4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create video illustrations from numerical experiments data with Paraview and Python 2</title>
      <link>https://bikulov.org/blog/2014/11/15/create-video-illustrations-from-numerical-experiments-data-with-paraview-and-python-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2014 01:56:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bikulov.org/blog/2014/11/15/create-video-illustrations-from-numerical-experiments-data-with-paraview-and-python-2/</guid>
      <description>See updated note.
One of the common tasks in computer modeling is visualization of numerical experiment as a movie. Usually it is one datafile per frame and target is to create frame-by-frame animation. If these files can be loaded and visualized in Paraview, it is easy to create the full video: load file in paraview with predefined parameters, create screenshot, load second file, etc. This process may be automated.
We will use latest stable build of Paraview from official site.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
