<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>openvpn on Bikulov&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://bikulov.org/tags/openvpn/</link>
    <description>Recent content in openvpn on Bikulov&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>ru</language>
    <copyright>Network Notes 2022</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2016 23:07:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bikulov.org/tags/openvpn/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Script for user configurations generation and sending at Ubuntu OpenVPN server</title>
      <link>https://bikulov.org/blog/2016/01/05/script-for-user-configurations-generation-and-sending-at-ubuntu-openvpn-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2016 23:07:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bikulov.org/blog/2016/01/05/script-for-user-configurations-generation-and-sending-at-ubuntu-openvpn-server/</guid>
      <description>Ubuntu has a very detailed documentation about OpenVPN server configuration. The key feature of this note is script for automatic generation of single-file client configurations (keys and certs are embedded) and sending them by email. Looks interesting? Read below!
ยง&amp;nbsp;Prerequisities All commands in this section must be executed as root user.
Update package list:
apt-get update apt-get -y upgrade Install needed packages (easy-rsa must be installed explicitly on modern Ubuntus):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for LXC: creation, autostart, OpenVPN and port forwarding to containers</title>
      <link>https://bikulov.org/blog/2014/10/09/tips-for-lxc-creation-autostart-openvpn-and-port-forwarding-to-containers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2014 10:02:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bikulov.org/blog/2014/10/09/tips-for-lxc-creation-autostart-openvpn-and-port-forwarding-to-containers/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve completed setting up my comfort set of LXC containers and want to save some points I spent a lot of time for or things for copy-paste.
I used the official Ubuntu Server Guide but note at Digital Ocean knowledge base also helped me a lot. I created 3 containers: one for vpn, one for site on Drupal and last one as www proxy for second one with nginx only.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Zip With VPN Client Keys and Configuration Files</title>
      <link>https://bikulov.org/blog/2013/07/31/creating-zip-with-vpn-client-keys-and-configuration-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2013 09:31:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bikulov.org/blog/2013/07/31/creating-zip-with-vpn-client-keys-and-configuration-files/</guid>
      <description>Depends on server configuration, each OpenVPN client needs configuration file (client.conf for *nix and client.ovpn for windows), certificate authority (ca.crt), [optional] tls auth file (ta.key), user crt and key.
Typical OpenVPN client configuration file looks like (ca and ta files in server subdirectory):
client remote &amp;lt;vpn server address&amp;gt; port 1194 proto udp dev tun dev-type tun ns-cert-type server reneg-sec 86400 comp-lzo yes verb 3 ca server/ca.crt cert &amp;lt;user crt&amp;gt; key &amp;lt;user key&amp;gt; tls-auth server/ta.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
